<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:abv="http://ossetic-studies.org/ns/abaevdict" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Abaev Dictionary: entry <hi rendition="#rend_italic">Artʼawyz</hi></title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt xml:base="../pubstmt.xml"><p>Translated from Russian in 2020 by Oleg Belyaev (ed.), Irina Khomchenkova, Julia
    Sinitsyna and Vadim Dyachkov.</p></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl xml:lang="ru"><author>Абаев, Василий Иванович</author>.
                        <title>Историко-этимологический словарь осетинского языка</title>. Т.
                        <biblScope unit="volume">I</biblScope>. A–Kʼ. <pubPlace>М.–Л.</pubPlace>:
                        <publisher>Наука</publisher>, <date>1958</date>. С. <biblScope unit="page">??–??</biblScope>.</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc xml:base="../encodingdesc.xml">
    <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_italic" scheme="css">font-variant: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_smallcaps" scheme="css">font-variant: small-caps;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_singlequotes" scheme="css" scope="q">quotes: "‘" "’";</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_doublequotes" scheme="css" scope="q">quotes: "«" "»";</rendition>
    </tagsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <entry xml:id="entry_Artʼawyz" xml:lang="os-x-iron">
                <form xml:id="form_d1951e66" type="lemma"><orth>Artʼawyz</orth></form>
                <usg><lang/></usg>
                <sense xml:id="sense_d1951e72"><abv:tr xml:lang="ru">
                        <q>мифическое существо, прогневившее Бога и в наказание прикованное к
                            луне</q>
                    </abv:tr><abv:tr xml:lang="en">
                        <q>a mythical creature that angered God and was chained to the moon as
                            punishment</q>
                    </abv:tr></sense>
                <abv:exampleGrp xml:id="exampleGrp_d1951e82">
                    <abv:example xml:id="example_d1951e84">
                        <quote>X˳ycaw ysfældysta cyppar xorzy; se ʽppæty sæjrag Artʼawyz, īnnæ læg,
                            īnnæ fys, īnnæ mænæw. Læg æmæ fys æmæ mænæwæn semæ ʽsfældysta fæjnæ
                            xæjræǵy: lægæn ūs, fysæn sæǧ, mænæwæn sysyly. Artʼawyz nyn xorzæn
                            fældyst wyd bærgæ, fælæ adæmty ardydta zyǧ˳ymmæʒinadyl. Wæd X˳ycaw
                            Wacillajæn zaǧta, Art’awyzy k˳yd yslasa jæxīmæ. Wacilla aværdta arvyl
                            mīǧy styg, nykʼkʼærcc æj lāsta æmæ jæ yelvæsta jæxīmæ… Wæd æj mæjy
                            mīdæg fsæjnag zægæltæj nyxx˳ydtoj. Art’awyz k˳y raīrvæza, wæd adæmy
                            baxærʒæn. Cæmæj ma raīrvæza, ūj tyxxæj aly k˳yrd dær qwamæ wældaj cæf
                            kæna qæsdarægyl</quote>
                        <abv:tr xml:lang="ru">
                            <q>Бог создал четыре блага: главное из них — Артауз, другое мужчина,
                                другое овца, другое пшеница. Вместе с мужчиной, овцой и пшеницей он
                                создал по чорту для каждого: для мужчины — женщину, для овцы — козу,
                                для пшеницы — <hi rendition="#rend_smallcaps">sуsуlу</hi> (сорняк, примесь которого делает муку
                                горькой). Артауз был сотворен нам на благо, но он стал учить людей
                                недоброму (превратному). Тогда Бог велел Уацилле, чтобы он втащил
                                Артауза к себе. Уацилла навел на небо тучу, ударил и поднял его к
                                себе… Тогда его железными гвоздями пригвоздили (пришили) внутри
                                луны. Если Артауз вырвется, то он сожрет людей. Чтобы он не
                                вырвался, каждый кузнец должен лишний раз ударять по наковальне</q>
                        </abv:tr>
                        <abv:tr xml:lang="en">
                            <q>God created four boons: the main one is Artauz, one more is man, one
                                more is sheep, one more is wheat. Together with a man, a sheep and
                                wheat, he created a devil for each: for a man — a woman, for a sheep
                                — a goat, for wheat — <hi rendition="#rend_smallcaps">sysyly</hi> (a weed whose admixture makes the
                                flour bitter). Artauz was created for our good, but he began to
                                teach people unkind (perverse) ways. Then God told Wacilla to drag
                                Artauz to him. Wacilla brought a cloud to the sky, struck and raised
                                him to himself… Then he was nailed (sewn) inside the moon with
                                iron nails. If Artauz breaks free, he will devour people. To prevent
                                him from escaping, every blacksmith must hit the anvil once more</q>
                        </abv:tr>
                        <bibl><ref type="bibl" target="#src_ЮОПам."/><biblScope>II
                            114</biblScope></bibl>
                    </abv:example>
                </abv:exampleGrp>
                <etym xml:lang="ru">Миф об Артаузе представляет один из вариантов Прометеевского
                    цикла (см. <ref type="xr" target="#entry_Amyran"/>). Имя %iArt’awyz%i восходит к
                        <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e168" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e108" xml:lang="xcl"><lang/>
                        <w>Art’avazd</w></mentioned>. Сын царя Арташеса и аланской принцессы Сатиник
                    Артавазд стал героем армянских эпических сказаний прометеевского типа, один из
                    вариантов которых приводит Моисей Хоренский: „…Арташес проклял его
                    (Артавазда), сказав: «если ты поедешь на охоту на свободный Масис, тебя захватят
                    каджи и света не увидишь более». Старухи также рассказывают про него, что он,
                    связанный железными цепями, заключен в какой-то пещере; что две собаки грызут
                    беспрестанно его цепи и он силится выйти и положить конец миру; но что от звука
                    ударов кузнечных молотов снова, говорят, оковы укрепляются. Поэтому также и в
                    наше время многие из кузнецов, следуя легенде, по воскресеньям ударяют трижды
                    или четырежды (молотом) о наковальню, чтобы укрепились, как говорят, цепи
                    Артавазда“ (<bibl><author>Моисей Хоренский</author><biblScope xml:lang="ru">История Армении. Перевод Н. О. Эмина, 1893, стр.
                            108</biblScope></bibl>. ). Имя %iArtavazd%i
                    иранского происхождения: <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e178" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e118" xml:lang="ira"><lang/>
                        <w>*Artavazdah-</w></mentioned>, <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e183" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e123" xml:lang="peo"><lang/>
                        <w>Ἀρταουάσδης</w></mentioned>, <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e189" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e129" xml:lang="ae"><lang/>
                        <w>Ašavazduh</w></mentioned>. В осетинский вошло, возможно, через грузинское
                    посредство: <mentioned xml:id="mentioned_d1951e134" xml:lang="grc"><lang/>
                        <w>Art’avazi</w>
                        <gloss><q>главный над чародеями</q></gloss></mentioned>
                            (<bibl><author>Чубинов</author></bibl>), <mentioned xml:id="mentioned_d1951e145" xml:lang="grc"><lang/>
                        <w>Atʼraozi</w>
                        <gloss><q>чорт</q></gloss></mentioned>, <mentioned xml:id="mentioned_d1951e153" xml:lang="grc"><w/>
                        <gloss><q>колдун</q></gloss></mentioned>
                        (<bibl><author>Беридзе</author></bibl>).</etym>
                <etym xml:lang="en">The Artauz myth is one of the variants of the Promethean cycle
                    (see <ref type="xr" target="#entry_Amyran"/>). The name %iArt’awyz%i goes back
                    to <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e108" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e168" xml:lang="xcl"><lang/>
                        <w>Art’avazd</w></mentioned>. The son of tsar Artashes and the Alanian
                    princess Satinik, Artavazd became the hero of Armenian epic tales of the
                    Promethean type, one of the variants of which is given by Moses Khorenatsi: ʽ…
                    Artashes cursed him (Artavazd), saying, “If you go hunting to the free Masis,
                    you will be captured by the Khaji and you will not see the light any moreʼ. The
                    old women also tell that he, bound by iron chains, is imprisoned in a cave; that
                    two dogs are incessantly gnawing at his chains and he is trying to get out and
                    put an end to the world; but that from the sound of blacksmithʽs hammers the
                    shackles are strengthened. Therefore, even nowadays, on Sundays many of the
                    blacksmiths, following the legend, strike three or four times (with a hammer) on
                    the anvil, so that, as they say, the chains of Artavazd are strengthened
                            (<bibl><author>Movses Khorenatsi</author><biblScope xml:lang="en">History of Armenia. Translation
                            by N. O. Emin, 1893, p. 108</biblScope></bibl>). The name %iArtavazd%i
                    is of Iranian origin: <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e118" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e178" xml:lang="ira"><lang/>
                        <w>*Artavazdah-</w></mentioned>, <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e123" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e183" xml:lang="peo"><lang/>
                        <w>Ἀρταουάσδης</w></mentioned>, <mentioned corresp="#mentioned_d1951e129" xml:id="mentioned_d1951e189" xml:lang="ae"><lang/>
                        <w>Ašavazduh</w></mentioned>. Probably, it came to Ossetic via Georgian:
                        <mentioned xml:id="mentioned_d1951e194" xml:lang="ka"><lang/>
                        <w>Art’avazi</w>
                        <gloss><q>head of the sorcerers</q></gloss></mentioned>
                            (<bibl><author>Chubinov</author></bibl>), <mentioned xml:id="mentioned_d1951e205" xml:lang="ka"><lang/>
                        <w>Atʼraozi</w>
                        <gloss><q>devil</q></gloss></mentioned>, <mentioned xml:id="mentioned_d1951e213" xml:lang="ka"><w/>
                        <gloss><q>sorcerer</q></gloss></mentioned>
                        (<bibl><author>Beridze</author></bibl>).</etym>
            </entry>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>