<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:abv="http://ossetic-studies.org/ns/abaevdict" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Abaev Dictionary: entry <hi rendition="#rend_italic">Safa</hi></title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt xml:base="../pubstmt.xml"><p>Translated from Russian in 2020 by Oleg Belyaev (ed.), Irina Khomchenkova, Julia
        Sinitsyna and Vadim Dyachkov.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl xml:lang="ru"><author>Абаев, Василий Иванович</author>.
          <title>Историко-этимологический словарь осетинского языка</title>. Т. <biblScope unit="volume">I</biblScope>. A–Kʼ. <pubPlace>М.–Л.</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>Наука</publisher>, <date>1958</date>. С. <biblScope unit="page">??–??</biblScope>.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc xml:base="../encodingdesc.xml">
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_italic" scheme="css">font-variant: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_smallcaps" scheme="css">font-variant: small-caps;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_singlequotes" scheme="css" scope="q">quotes: "‘" "’";</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend_doublequotes" scheme="css" scope="q">quotes: "«" "»";</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <entry xml:id="entry_Safa" xml:lang="os" abv:completeness="incomplete">
        <form xml:id="form_d5158e66" type="lemma"><orth>Safa</orth></form>
        <sense xml:id="sense_d5158e69">
          <note xml:lang="ru" type="comment">в старой осетинской религии и мифологии — божество
            очага и надочажной цепи (<ref type="xr" target="#entry_ræxys"/>). Ему приписывается
            изготовление первой надочажной цепи, спущенной им с неба в подарок людям. В некоторых
            сказаниях и обрядах он выступает как бог-кузнец и как бы дублирует Курдалагона. <q
              rendition="#rend_doublequotes">Чтобы предохранить здоровье детей, им изготовлялись
              амулеты в честь Сафы. На третий день великого поста, в среду, давали кузнецу
              раскаливать самые мелкие прутики железа: эти кусочки зашивали в ладонке... и
              заставляли детей носить на шее... Принося присягу, осетин становится перед очагом и,
              держась за цепь, говорит: <q rendition="#rend_doublequotes">Клянусь этим пречистым
                золотом Сафы....</q>. При брачном обряде шафер обводит невесту вокруг очага и
              поручает ее покровительству Сафы </q>. (<bibl><ref type="bibl"
                target="#src_Миллер_Вс._ОЭ"/><biblScope>II 248 — 249</biblScope></bibl>). В
            молитвенных обращениях Сафа именуется обычно <w>wælart Safa</w>
            <q rendition="#rend_doublequotes">надочажный Сафа</q>. О культе надочажной цепи см.
            также под словом <ref type="xr" target="#entry_ræxys"/></note>
          <note xml:lang="en" type="comment">the deity of the hearth and the hearth chain (<ref
              type="xr" target="#entry_ræxys"/>) in the old Ossetian religion and mythology. This
            deity is credited with creation of the first fireplace chain that was brought down from
            the sky as a gift to people. In some legends and rituals he appears as a god-smith and
            thus seemingly duplicates Kurdalægon. <q rendition="#rend_doublequotes">In order to
              protect children's health, amulets in honour of Safa were made by him. On the third
              day of the great lent, on Wednesday, they let a smith heat the smallest iron twigs:
              these small pieces were sewn into amulets... and they made children wear it around a
              neck. Taking an oath, an Ossetian stands in front of the hearth, holds the hearth
              chain and says: <q rendition="#rend_doublequotes">I swear on this purest gold of
                Safa...</q>. During the mating ritual the best man leads the bride round the hearth
              and delegates her to the patronage of Safa.</q>. (<bibl><ref type="bibl"
                target="#src_Миллер_Вс._ОЭ"/><biblScope>II 248 — 249</biblScope></bibl>). In the
            prayer appeals Safa is usually called <w>wælart Safa</w>
            <q rendition="#rend_doublequotes">above-hearth Safa</q>. About the cult of the hearth
            chain see also above the word <ref type="xr" target="#entry_ræxys"/></note>
        </sense>
        <exampleGrp xmlns="http://ossetic-studies.org/ns/abaevdict">
          <example>
            <quote xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><oRef>Safa</oRef> jæ dywwadæs k˳yncy razdæxta
              Batyraʒmæ</quote>
            <tr xml:lang="ru">
              <q xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Сафа свои двенадцать кузнечных мехов направил
                на Батрадза</q>
            </tr>
            <tr xml:lang="en">
              <q xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Safa pointed all his twelve blacksmith's
                bellows on Batyradz</q>
            </tr>
            <bibl xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><ref type="bibl" target="#src_ЮОПам."/>
              <biblScope>I 150</biblScope></bibl>
          </example>
          <example>
            <quote xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><oRef>Safajy</oRef> fyrt... jæ ʒyppæj sīsta
              xærynkʼa... xærynkʼajæ aliwyrdta fys æmæ dywwæ læppūjy; ūdon argævstoj fys, yskodtoj
              fīzonǵytæ</quote>
            <tr xml:lang="ru">
              <q xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">сын Сафы достал из кармана ножичек; из ножичка
                выскочили овца и два мальчика; они зарезали овцу и приготовили шашлык</q>
            </tr>
            <tr xml:lang="en">
              <q xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">the son of Safa got out of the pocket a little
                knife; from a knife a sheep and two boys jumped out; they slaughtered the sheep and
                made a kebab</q>
            </tr>
            <bibl xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><ref type="bibl" target="#src_ОЭ"/>
              <biblScope>I 48</biblScope></bibl>
          </example>
          <example xml:lang="os-x-digor">
            <usg xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><lang/></usg>
            <quote xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">ærtæ boni kи racæwa rajguruni fæste wædta...
              wæras iskænuncæ, kʼeretæ skænuncæ, ærtæ Xucawæn, ærtæ Madæ-Majrænæn, ærtæ Bundoræn,
                <oRef>Safajæn</oRef> ba ærtæ gubori, æma sæ raxæssuncæ bælasi bunmæ...; avdænæ æd
              suvællon... æriværuncæ ræxisi buni æma skovuncæ: <q>Walart <oRef>Safa</oRef>, dæ
                iwazæg...</q></quote>
            <tr xml:lang="ru">
              <q xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">когда пройдет три дня после рождения (ребенка),
                тогда готовят брагу, пекут пироги, три Богу, три Богоматери, три Домовому, а для
                Сафа три лепешки, и выносят их под дерево...; колыбель вместе с ребенком ставят под
                надочажную цепь и молятся: <q>Надочажный Сафа, да будет (ребенок) под твоим
                  покровительством (<q>твоим гостем</q>)</q>
              </q>
            </tr>
            <tr xml:lang="en">
              <q xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">when three days since the birth (of a child)
                are over, they cook a home-brewed beer, bake pies, three pies are dedicated to God,
                other three ones to Mother of God, three ones to the Browny, but for Safa three
                flatbreads are prepared and people carry them under the tree... People put the
                cradle with the child under the hearth chain and pray: <q>Above-hearth Safa, let the
                  child be under your patronage (<q>your guest</q>)</q></q>
            </tr>
            <bibl xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><ref type="bibl" target="src_Диг. сказ."/>
              <biblScope>58 — 59</biblScope></bibl>
          </example>
        </exampleGrp>
        <etym xml:lang="ru">Типологически весьма древнее божество. Прототипом его была скифская
          богиня Табити, которую <name>Геродот</name> отождествляет с греческой богиней домашнего
          очага Гестией. После христианизации алан в X в. многим древним языческим богам и
          календарным праздникам были присвоены имена популярных в восточной христианской церкви
          святых. Так, праздник зимнего солноворота получил название <mentioned xml:lang="os"><lang/>
            <w>Basiltæ</w>
            <gloss>(св. Василий Великий)</gloss></mentioned>, праздник начала сенокоса — <ref
            type="xr" target="#entry_Atynæg"/> (св. Афиноген Севастийский), бог домашнего скота —
            <ref type="xr" target="#entry_Fælværa"/> (св. Флор и Лавр), бог волков — <ref type="xr"
            target="#entry_Tūtyr"/> (св. Федор Тирский) и т. п. Не исключено, что и древний бог
          домашнего очага после христианизации стал называться <oRef>Safa</oRef>, т. е. Савва,
            <mentioned xml:lang="grc"><lang/>
            <w>Σáββαç</w></mentioned>, по имени святого Саввы Освященного (родом из Каппадокии, умер
          в Иерусалиме в 532 г.). Основанный им монастырь близ Иерусалима был широко известен в
          восточной церкви и привлекал много паломников. — Связанный с именем <oRef>Safa</oRef>
          культ надочажной цепи хранит отголосок культа железа: на заре железного века надочажная
          цепь была одним из немногих железных предметов домашнего обихода и уже в силу этого была
          окружена ореолом. <bibl><ref type="bibl" target="#ref_ОЯФ_I"/>
            <biblScope>193</biblScope></bibl>.</etym>
        <etym xml:lang="en">Safa is typologically a very ancient deity. His prototype was the
          Skythic goddess Tabiti which <name>Herodotus</name> equates with the Greek goddess of the
          home hearth Hestia. After the Christianisation of Alanians in the 10th century, many
          ancient pagan gods and calendar holidays were given the names of saints, popular in the
          Eastern Christian Church. Thus, the holiday in honour of the Winter solstice got the name
            <mentioned xml:lang="os"><lang/>
            <w>Basiltæ</w>
            <gloss>(Saint Basil the Great)</gloss></mentioned>, the holiday dedicated to the start
          of the hay harvest — <ref type="xr" target="#entry_Atynæg"/> (Saint Athinogen Sebastian),
          the god of the livestock — <ref type="xr" target="#entry_Fælværa"/> (Saints Florus and
          Laurus), the god of wolves — <ref type="xr" target="#entry_Tūtyr"/> (Saint Theodore Tiron)
          and so on. It is not excluded that an ancient god of the home hearth after the
          Christianisation started to be called <oRef>Safa</oRef>, i. e. Sabbas, <mentioned
            xml:lang="grc"><lang/>
            <w>Σáββαç</w></mentioned> after the name of Sabbas the Sanctified (he was born in
          Cappadocia, died in Jerusalem in 532). The monastery near Jerusalem that he grounded was
          wide-known in the Eastern Church and attracted many pilgrims. — The cult of the hearth
          chain connected with the name <oRef>Safa</oRef> preserves an echo of the cult of iron: at
          the down of the iron age fireplace chain was one of the very few iron household items and
          by that reason alone was surrounded by a special aura. <bibl><ref type="bibl"
              target="#ref_ОЯФ_I"/>
            <biblScope>193</biblScope></bibl>.</etym>
      </entry>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
